So when I decided to create an art piece in Manshiyat Naser,
عندما قررت خلق قطعة فنية في منشية ناصر،
the neighborhood of the Cairo garbage collectors in Egypt,
وهي حي لجامعي القمامة في القاهرة في مصر،
I never thought this project would be
لم أكن أتخيل أن هذا المشروع سيكون
the most amazing human experience that I would ever live.
أكثر تجربة إنسانية روعة عشتها قط.
As an artist, I had this humanist intention
كفنان، كانت لي نية إنسانية
of beautifying a poor and neglected neighborhood
لتجميل حي فقير متخلى عنه
by bringing art to it and hopefully shining light on this isolated community.
من خلال جلب الفن على أمل إلقاء الضوء على هذه المجموعة المهمشة.
The first time I heard about this Christian Coptic community
كانت أول مرة سمعت فيها عن المجتمع المسيحي القبطي
was in 2009 when the Egyptian authorities under the regime of Hosni Mubarak
سنة 2009، حين قررت السلطات المصرية في عهد حسني مبارك
decided to slaughter 300,000 pigs using the pretext of H1N1 virus.
ذبح 300000 خنزير، تحت ذريعة وجود فيروس إتش 1 إن 1.
Originally, they are pig breeders.
في الأصل، فهم مربو خنازير.
Their pigs and other animals are fed with the organic waste
تتغذى خنازيرهم وحيوانات أخرى على البقايا العضوية
that they collect on a daily basis.
التي يجمعونها يوميًا.
This event killed their livelihood.
فكان الحدث أن قضى على معيشتهم.
The first time I entered Manshiyat Naser, it felt like a maze.
في المرة الأولى التي دخلت فيها منشية ناصر، أحسست أنني في متاهة.
I was looking for the St. Simon Monastery on the top of the Muqattam Mountain.
كنت أبحث عن دير القديس سيمون من على جبل المقطم.
So you go right, then straight, then right again, then left
عليك أن تذهب يمينًا، ثم إلى الأمام، ثم يمينًا مرة أخرى، ثم يسارًا
to reach all the way to the top.
لتصل رأسًا إلى القمة.
But to reach there, you must dodge between the trucks overpacked with garbage
ولكن لكي تصل هناك، عليك أن تراوغ شاحنات ممتلئة عن آخرها بالقمامة
and slalom between the tuk-tuks,
وبين عربات التكتك،
the fastest vehicle to move around in the neighborhood.
وهي العربة الأسرع المستعملة للتحرك داخل الحي.
The smell of the garbage unloaded from those trucks was intense,
كانت رائحة القمامة التي يتم تنزيلها من الشاحنات قوية جدًا،
and the noise of the traffic was loud and overbearing.
ضوضاء حركة الناقلات لا تطاق.
Add to it the din created by the crushers in those warehouses along the way.
أضف إلى ذلك الضجيج الناتج عن الكسارات داخل المستودعات المنتشرة على طول الطريق.
From outside it looks chaotic, but everything is perfectly organized.
من الخارج يبدو المنظر فوضويًا، لكن كل شيء منظم جدًا.
The Zaraeeb, that’s how they call themselves,
الزرايب، هكذا يسمون أنفسهم،
which means the pig breeders,
وتعني مربو الخنازير،
have been collecting the garbage of Cairo
يجمعون القمامة من القاهرة
and sorting it in their own neighborhood for decades.
ويقومون بفرزها في حيهم منذ عقود.
They have developed one of the most efficient
لقد طوروا بذلك واحدًا من أكثر الأنظمة فعالية
and highly profitable systems on a global level.
وأعلاها مردودًا على المستوى العالمي.
Still, the place is perceived as dirty, marginalized and segregated
مع ذلك، فلا زال يُرى المكان على أنه متسخ، مهمش ومعزول
because of their association with the trash.
بسبب صلتهم بالقمامة.
So my initial idea was to create an anamorphic piece,
إذًا فقد كانت فكرتي الأساسية أن أخلق قطعة بصرية متعددة القطع،
a piece that you can only see from one vantage point.
قطعة يمكن أن تراها من نقطة معينة.
I wanted to challenge myself artistically by painting over several buildings
كنت أريد أن أن أتحدى نفسي فنيًا من خلال الرسم على عدة بنايات
and having it only fully visible from one point on the Muqattam Mountain.
يمكن أن ترى بشكل كامل من على قمة جبل المقطم.
The Muqattam Mountain is the pride of the community.
جبل المقطم هو مفخرة لذلك المجتمع.
This is where they built the St. Simon Monastery,
هناك حيث بنوا دير القديس سيمون،
a 10,000-seat cave church that they carved into the mountain itself.
وهو كنيسة على شكل كهف تضم 10000 مقعد، قاموا بنحتها في الجبل ذاته.
So, the first time I stood on top of the mountain
لذا، في المرة الأولى التي وقفت فيها على الجبل
and I looked at the neighborhood,
ونظرت إلى الحي،
I asked myself, how on earth will I convince all those owners
تساءلت، كيف لي أن أقنع كل ملاك البيوت أولئك
to let me paint on their buildings?
لكي يسمحوا لي بالرسم عليها؟
And then Magd came.
حينها جاء مجد.
Magd is a guide from the Church.
مجد هو دليل سياحي من الكنيسة.
He told me the only person I needed to convince was Father Samaan,
أخبرني أن الشخص الوحيد الذي عليّ إقناعه هو الأب سمعان،
who is the leader of the community.
وهو القائد في المجتمع.
But to convince Father Samaan, I needed to convince Mario,
ولكن لكي أقنع الأب سمعان، كان علي أن أقنع ماريو،
who is a Polish artist who moved to Cairo 20 years ago
وهو فنان بولوني انتقل إلى القاهرة قبل 20 سنة
and who created all the artwork of the Cave Church.
وهو الذي خلق كل العمل الفني في الكنيسة الكهف.
I am really grateful to Mario. He was the key of the project.
أنا ممتن جدًا لماريو. فقد كان دوره مهمًا في المشروع.
He managed to get me a meeting with Father Samaan,
فقد نجح في تحديد لقاء لي مع الأب سمعان،
and surprisingly, he loved the idea.
وكانت المفاجأة، أن أحب الفكرة.
He asked me about where I painted before
سألني أين رسمت من قبل
and how I will make it happen.
وكيف يمكن تحقيق مشروعي.
And he was mainly concerned by what I was going to write.
وقد كان قلقًا أكثر حيال ما كنت سأكتبه.
In every work that I create, I write messages
في كل عمل أقوم به، أكتب رسائل
with my style of Arabic calligraphy.
بأسلوبي في الخط العربي.
I make sure those messages are relevant to the place where I am painting
أتأكد من أن رسائلي تتوافق مع المكان الذي أرسم فيه
but have this universal dimension,
لكنها تحمل أيضًا بعدًا عالميًا،
so anybody around the world can relate to it.
حتي يتمكن أي شخص في العالم أن يحس بها.
So for Manshiyat Naser,
إذًا بالنسبة لمنشية ناصر،
I decided to write in Arabic the words of St. Athanasius of Alexandria,
قررت أن أكتب بالعربية كلمات القديس أثناسيوس بابا الإسكندرية،
a Coptic bishop from the third century,
وهو أسقف قبطي من القرن الثالث،
who said: (Arabic),
الذي قال: إن أراد أحد أن يبصر نور الشمس، فإن عليه أن يمسح عينيه.
which means in English,
والتي تعني بالإنجليزية،
"Anyone who wants to see the sunlight clearly
إن أراد أحد أن يبصر نور الشمس بوضوح،
needs to wipe his eyes first."
فإن عليه أن يمسح عينيه أولا.
It was really important for me
فكان ذلك مهمًا بالنسبة لي
that the community felt connected to the words.
أن يحس أفراد الجماعة أنهم متصلون بالكلمات.
And for me this quote was perfectly reflecting the spirit of the project.
وبالنسبة لي كانت هذه العبارة تعكس بشكل تام روح المشروع.
So Father Samaan blessed the project,
فكان أن بارك الأب سمعان المشروع،
and his approval brought all the residents on board.
وموافقته جعلت جميع السكان ينضمون إلينا.
Hundreds of liters of paint, a dozen blue manual lifts,
مئات اللترات من الصباغة، والعشرات من الرافعات اليدوية الزرقاء،
several trips back and forth to Cairo,
والعديد من الرحلات من وإلى القاهرة،
a strong and solid team from France, North Africa, Middle East and the US,
فريق قوي من فرنسا، شمال أفريقيا، الشرق الأوسط والولايات المتحدة،
and after a year of planning and logistics, there we are,
وبعد عام من التخطيط واللوجيستية، ها نحن ذا،
my team and some members from the local community
فريقي وبعض من أفراد المجتمع المحلي
creating a piece that will spread over 50 buildings,
نخلق قطعة ستنتشر فوق 50 بناية،
some filling up the space of the calligraphy
بعضهم يملأ الفراغ في الخط
that I trace with colors.
الذي رسمته بالألوان.
Here some blue, there some yellow, there some orange.
هنا بعض الأزرق، وبعض الأصفر، وبعض البرتقالي.
Some others carrying some sand bags
بعضهم يحمل أكياس الرمل
and putting them on the top of the buildings
ويضعها في أعلى البنايات
to hold those manual lifts,
لكي تثبت الرافعات اليدوية،
and some others assembling and disassembling those same lifts
وبعضهم يركب أو يفك نفس هذه الرافعات
and moving them around the different buildings.
وينقلها إلى بنايات أخرى.
At the beginning of the project,
في بداية المشروع،
I numbered all those buildings on my sketch,
وضعت أرقامًا على كل هذه البنايات على رسمي الأولي،
and there was no real interaction with the community.
ولم يكن هناك أي تفاعل حقيقي مع الناس.
People didn’t get the point of all this.
لم يفهم الناس الهدف من هذا كله.
But fast enough, those building numbers became family names.
لكن بسرعة، أصبحت هذه الأرقام أسماء عوائل.
The first building was the house of Uncle Ibrahim.
المبنى الأول كان منزل العم إبراهيم.
Uncle Ibrahim is such an enthusiastic person.
العم إبراهيم رجل متحمس جدًا.
He was always singing and making jokes,
كان دائمًا يغني ويحكي النكت،
and his daughters and sons saved me from his bull
وقد أنقذني أبناؤه وبناته من ثوره
who wanted to attack me on the fourth floor.
الذي أراد أن يهاجمني في الطايق الرابع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Actually, the bull saw me from the window and came out on the balcony.
في الواقع، فقد رآني الثور من النافذة، وخرج من الشرفة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah.
أجل.
Uncle Ibrahim was always hanging out on the balcony
كان العم إبراهيم دائمًا يخرج للشرفة
and talking to me while I was painting.
ويتحدث إليّ بينما كنت أرسم.
I remember him saying that he didn’t go to the mountain for 10 years,
أتذكر أنه أخبرني أنه لم يذهب للجبل منذ 10 سنين،
and that he never takes a day off.
وأنه لم يأخذ يومًا للراحة قط.
He said that if he stopped working, who will stop the garbage?
قال أنه إن توقف هو عن العمل، من سيوقف القمامة؟
But surprisingly, at the end of the project,
وكانت المفاجأة، عند نهاية المشروع،
he came all the way to the mountain to look at the piece.
أن جاء إلى الجبل لرؤية القطعة.
He was really proud to see his house painted,
كان فخورًا جدًا حين رأى بيته وعليه رسم،
and he said that this project was a project of peace and --
وقال أن هذا المشروع مشروع سلام--
sorry --
المعذرة--
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
He said that it was a project of peace and unity
قال إنه كان مشروع سلام ووحدة
and that it brought people together.
وأنه قد جمع الناس مع بعضها البعض.
So his perception towards the project changed,
لذا فتصوره عن المشروع قد تغير،
and my perception towards the community changed also,
وتصوري عن المجتمع تغير أيضًا،
and towards what they do.
وحيال ما يقومون به.
All the garbage that everybody is disgusted by is not theirs.
كل القمامة التي يتقزز منها الجميع ليست قمامتهم.
They just work out of it.
هم فقط يعيشون من خلالها.
Actually, they don’t live in the garbage. They live from the garbage.
في الواقع هم لا يعيشون في القمامة. هم يعيشون من القمامة.
So I started doubting myself and wondering
فبدأت أشك في نفسي وأتساءل
what was the real purpose of this whole project?
ما المغزى الحقيقي من هذا المشروع كله؟
It was not about beautifying a place by bringing art to it.
لم يكن من أجل تجميل مكان عن طريق جلب فن إليه.
It was about switching perception and opening a dialogue
بل كان عن تغيير تصور وفتح حوار
on the connection that we have with communities that we don’t know.
عن الصلة التي تجمعنا بمجتمعات لا نعرفها.
So day after day,
لذا يومًا بعد يوم،
the calligraphy circle was taking shape,
كانت دائرة الخط تأخذ شكلًا،
and we were always excited to go back on the mountain to look at the piece.
وكنا متحمسين دائمًا للعودة للجبل لننظر إلى القطعة.
And standing exactly at this point every day made my realize
والوقوف في هذا المكان بالضبط كل يوم جعلني أدرك
the symbolism behind this anamorphic piece.
الرمزية وراء قطعة متعددة القطع.
If you want to see the real image of somebody,
إن كنت تريد الصورة الحقيقة لشخص ما،
maybe you should change your angle.
ربما عليك أن تغير زواية نظرك.
There was doubts and difficulties,
كانت هناك شكوك وصعوبات،
like fears and stress.
مثل مخاوف وتوترات.
It wasn't simple to work in such environments,
لم يكن من السهل العمل في مثل تلك البيئة،
sometimes having pigs under you while you paint
في بعض الأحيان، هناك خنازير أسفل منك وأنت ترسم،
or climbing a stack of garbage to reach a lift.
أو أن يكون عليك أن تتسلق أكوام القمامة لتصل إلى الرافعة.
But we all got over the fear of the heights, the swinging lifts,
لكننا جميعًا تجاوزنا الخوف من الارتفاعات، والرافعات المتأرجحة،
the strength of the smell
وقوة الرائحة
and also the stress of not finishing on time.
وتوتر عدم إنهاء المشروع في الوقت المحدد.
But the kindness of all those people made us forget everything.
لكن لطف كل هؤلاء الناس جعلنا ننسى كل شيء.
The building number 3 was the house of Uncle Bakheet and Aunty Fareeda.
المبنى رقم 3 كان منزل العم بخيت والخالة فريدة.
In Egyptian, they have this expression that says, "Ahsen Nas,"
باللهجة المصرية، لديهم عبارة "أحسن ناس"،
which means "the best people."
والتي تعني "أحسن الناس".
They were the best people.
كانوا هم أحسن ناس.
We used to take our break in front of their houses,
كنا نأخذ فترات استراحة أمام منازلهم،
and all the kids of the neighborhood
وكان كل أطفال الحي
used to join us.
ينضمون إلينا.
I was impressed and amazed by the kids of Manshiyat Naser.
كنت مندهشًا من أطفال منشية ناصر.
For the first few days, they were always refusing anything we were offering them,
في الأيام الأولى، كانوا دائمًا يرفضون أي شيء نقدمه لهم،
even a snack or a drink.
حتى قطعة حلوى أو مشروبًا.
So I asked Aunty Fareeda, "Why is that?"
سألت الخالة فريدة، "ما السبب؟"
And she told me they teach their kids to refuse anything
أخبرتني أنهم يعلمون أولادهم أن يرفضوا أي شيء
from somebody that they don't know
من أي شخص لا يعرفونه
because maybe this person needs it more than they do.
لأنه ربما ذلك الشخص يحتاجه أكثر منهم.
So at this exact point I realized actually
إذًا وفي هذه اللحظة بالذات أدركت
the Zaraeeb community was the ideal context
أن مجتمع الزرايب هو النطاق الأفضل
to raise the topic of perception.
لطرح موضوع التصور والفهم.
We need to question our level of misconception
علينا أن نعيد النظر في مستوى سوء الفهم
and judgment we can have as a society
والحكم الذي نحمله كمجتمع
upon communities based on their differences.
عن الجماعات استنادًا إلى اختلافاتهم عنا.
I remember how we got delayed on Uncle Ibrahim's house
أتذكر أننا تأخرنا في العمل على منزل العم إبراهيم
when his pigs that are bred on the rooftop
حين كانت خنازير المرباة على سطح المنزل
were eating the sand bags that hold the lifts.
تأكل أكياس الرمل التي كانت تثبت الرافعات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The house of Uncle Bakheet and Aunty Fareeda
كان منزل العم بخيت والخالة فريدة
was this kind of meeting point.
بمثابة نقطة تجمع.
Everybody used to gather there.
كان الجميع يجتمع هناك.
I think this is what Uncle Ibrahim meant
أعتقد أن هذا ما كان العم إبراهيم يعنيه
when he said that was a project of peace and unity,
حين قال أن المشروع هو مشروع سلام ووحدة،
because I really felt that people were coming together.
لأنني أحسست فعلًا أن الناس كانت تجتمع مع بعضها.
Everyone was greeting us with a smile, offering us a drink
كان الجميع يحيينا بالابتسامة، ويقدمون لنا مشروبًا
or inviting us into their own house for lunch.
أو يدعوننا إلى منازلهم لتناول الغداء.
Sometime, you are at the first level of a building,
أحيانًا تكون في الطابق الأول من البناية،
and somebody opens his window and offers you some tea.
فيفتح أحد النافذة ليقدم لك الشاي.
And then the same thing happens on the second floor.
ونفس الشيء يحدث في الطابق الثاني.
And you keep going all the way to the top.
وهكذا دواليك حتى تصل إلى الأعلى.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I think I never drink as much tea as I did in Egypt.
أعتقد أنني لم أشرب شايًا بهذه الكمية كما شربت في مصر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And to be honest with you, we could have finished earlier,
ولكي أكون صادقًا معكم، كان بإمكاننا أن ننهي المشروع مبكرًا،
but I think it took us three weeks because of all those tea breaks.
لكن أخذ منا الأمر 3 أسابيع بسبب كل استراحات الشاي هذه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In Egypt, they have another expression, which is "Nawartouna,"
في مصر، لديهم عبارة أخرى، وهي "نورتونا"،
which means, "You brought light to us."
والتي تعني "جلبتم لنا النور".
In Manshiyat Naser they were always telling us this.
في منشية ناصر، كانوا دائمًا ما يقولونها لنا.
The calligraphy, actually --
الخط المرسوم، في الواقع--
I used a white glow-in-the-dark paint for the calligraphy
استعملت صباغة بيضاء تتوهج في الظلام في كتابة الخط
so at the end of the project, we rented some black light projectors
ففي نهاية المشروع، استأجرنا كاشفات ضوئية سوداء
and lit up the whole neighborhood,
وأنرنا الحي كله،
surprising everybody around.
وفاجأنا من في الجوار.
We wanted to tell them
كنا نريد أن نقول لهم
that they are the ones who brought light to us.
أنهم هم من جلبوا لنا النور.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The Zaraeeb community are strong, honest, hard workers,
مجتمع الزرايب، أقوياء، صادقون ومجتهدون،
and they know their value.
ويعرفون قيمتهم.
The people of Cairo call them "the Zabaleen,"
سكان القاهرة يسمونهم" الزبالين"،
which means "the people of the garbage,"
وتعني "أصحاب القمامة"،
but ironically, the people of Manshiyat Naser
لكن المفارقة أن سكان منشية ناصر
call the people of Cairo the Zabaleen.
يسمون سكان القاهرة بالزبالين.
They say, they are the ones who produce the garbage, not them.
يقولون أنهم هم من ينتجون القمامة، وليسوا هم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The goal was to leave something to this community,
كان الهدف أن نترك شيئًا للمجتمع،
but I feel that they are the ones who left something in our lives.
لكنني أشعر أتهم هم من تركوا أثرًا في حياتنا.
The art piece at some point will disappear, vanish,
في نقطة ما، ستختفي تلك القطعة الفنية وستتلاشى،
so I might need to go back and paint over it.
لذا فربما علي أن أعود لأعيد رسمه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It was about the experience,
كان الأمر متعلقًا بالتجربة،
about the story,
وبالقصة،
about the moment.
وباللحظة.
From the streets of the neighborhood,
من شوارع الأحياء،
the painting appears in fragments,
فإن الرسم يظهر على شكل قطع،
isolated from one another,
منفصلة عن بعضها البعض،
standing alone.
واقفة بمفردها.
But connected with the sign of calligraphy
لكنها متصلة برموز الخط
that today reveals the powerful message that we should all think about
والتي تبين اليوم الرسالة الحقيقية التي علينا جميعا أن نفكر بها
before we want to judge somebody.
قبل أن ننوي الحكم على أي أحد.
Anyone who wants to see the sunlight clearly
إن أراد أحد أن يبصر نور الشمس،
needs to wipe his eyes first.
فإن عليه أن يمسح عينيه.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)